Finding Aid for William Harlan Stoneman Papers, 1928-1974
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William Harlan Stoneman papers 1928-1974
Stoneman, William Harlan, 1904-
8675 Aa 2
Foreign correspondent with the Chicago Daily News; correspondence, photographs, and scrapbooks of his news articles.
6 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by William H. Stoneman (donor no. 5605 ) in 1974.
The collection is open to research.
William Stoneman was born March 15, 1904 in Grand Rapids, Michigan. As a youth, he moved first to Dexter, then to Ann Arbor, Michigan. He graduated from Ann Arbor High School in 1921 and from the University of Michigan in 1925. Stoneman began his career in journalism as a police reporter with the Chicago Daily News. Subsequently, he was offered an overseas assignment in Scandinavia reporting on world events, 1928-1929. He would remain a foreign correspondent for the rest of his career, with assignments in Rome, 1929-1931, Moscow, 1931-1935, Ethiopia, 1935-1936, London, 1936-1946 and 1958-1968, and in Paris, 1949-1958 and 1968. During World War II, Stoneman served as war correspondent with British forces in France, 1939-1940, and with US forces in Tunisia, Italy, France, and Germany, 1942-1945. After the war, he served as special adviser to the secretary-general of the United Nations, 1946-1949. In 1969, Stoneman was a visiting professor at the University of Michigan. He died in April 1987.
The collection includes correspondence, scrapbooks, photograph albums, and other material concerning his newspaper career, especially his reporting of the war in Ethiopia, the outbreak of war in France, 1939-1940, and the "Hungarian Rebellion" of 1956. The collection is organized in to three series: Correspondence, undated and 1931-1970; Career and personal materials; Photographs, 1925-1960s, including a photo album from the Hungarian revolution; and Scrapbooks, 1928-1973.
Subjects:
Chicago daily news.; Ethiopia.; France.; Great Britain.; Hungary.; Italo-Ethiopian War, 1935-1936.; Journalists--Illinois--Chicago.; American newspapers--Illinois--Chicago.; Soviet Union.; World War, 1939-1945.; Foreign correspondents--United States.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Stoneman, William Harlan, 1904-; Foreign correspondents--United States.; Hungary--History--Revolution, 1956.; Khrushchev, Nikita Sergeevich, 1894-1971.; War correspondents--American.
Contributors
Alsop, Joseph, 1910-1989; Bohlen, Charles E. (Charles Eustis), 1904-1974; Bruce, David Kirkpatrick Este.; Bunche, Ralph J. (Ralph Johnson), 1904-1971.; Cowles, John, 1898-1983.; Daniel, Clifton, 1912-2000; Gunther, John, 1901-1970.; Knox, Frank, 1874-1944.; Lie, Trygve, 1896-1968.; Mowrer, Edgar Ansel, 1892-1977; Sheean, Vincent, 1899-1975; Shirer, William L. (William Lawrence), 1904-1993.; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965.; Sylvester, Arthur, 1901-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence 1931-1970
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1931-1935 (Box 1)
  - 1936-1940 (Box 1)
  - 1941-1950 (Box 1)
  - 1951-1955 (Box 1)
  - 1956-1960 (Box 1)
  - 1961-1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966-1970 (Box 1)
- Career and personal materials
  - Personal publicity 1925-1969 (Box 1)
  - Papers concerning activities in France 1939 (Box 1)
  - Papers concerning the "Sitzkreig" in France 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - Diary notes on London at the beginning of the war September 1939 (Box 1)
  - Notes on Russia 1932-1935 (Box 1)
  - Papers concerning the war in Ethiopia 1935-1936 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, speeches, and talks (Box 1)
  - Stoneman autobiography (Box 1)
- Photographs 1925-1960s
  - Photograph album concerning "Hungarian Rebellion" 1956 (Box 1)
  - Photograph album of visit of Nikita Khrushchev to Oslo in 1964 and of his visit to Finland in 1957 (Box 1)
  - Photograph album from Foreign Ministers Conference in Berlin January-February 1954 (Box 1)
    (include informal photos of British and American foreign correspondents)
  - Albums of personal and professional photographs highlighting his career, colleagues and acquaintances circa 1928-1960s, 3 volumes (Box 1)
  - Album containing passports and relating miscellanea (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks 1928-1973
  - Scrapbooks August 1928-May 1939, 10 volumes (Box 2)
  - Scrapbooks May 1939-March 1946, May 1949-June 1951, 6 volumes (Box 3)
  - Scrapbooks July 1951-March 1958, 6 volumes (Box 4)
  - Scrapbooks April 1958-February 1963, 4 volumes (Box 5)
  - Scrapbooks February 1963-1973, 3 volumes (Box 6)
    (includes loose clippings)
Selective Index to Correspondence.
Alsop, Joseph, 1910-
October 11, 1965, October 22, 1965
Bohlen, Charles E. (Charles Eustis), 1904-
January 4, 1953, August 25, 1958, March 9, 1959, October 1, 1959, April 11, 1962, September 5, 1962, June 14, 1966
Bruce, David Kirkpatrick Este.
Mar 13, 1961, May 6, 1963, November 10, 1965
Bunce, Ralph J. (Ralph Johnson), 1904-1971.
July 17, 1959, August 9, 1960, January 31, 1961
Cowles, John, 1898-1983
October 10, 1955, October 24, 1955
Daniel, Elbert Clifton, 1912-
Undated
Gunther, John, 1901-1970.
April 6, 1936, July 21, 1936
Knox, Frank, 1874-1944.
Nov. 2, 1931, March 4, 1932, April 1, 1932, April 6, 1932, June 20, 1932, January 12, 1933, March 22, 1933, July 16, 1934, December 15, 1934
December 18, 1936, February 11, 1937, March 5, 1937, December 15, 1937, December 18, 1937, December 20, 1937, January 7, 1938, January 12, 1938, March 28, 1938, May 18, 1938, July 20, 1938, November 15, 1938, December 5, 1938
Lie, Trygve, 1896-1968.
July 12, 1949, August 3, 1949, June 10, 1953
Mowrer, Edgar Ansel, 1892-
March 29, 1933
Sheean, Vincent, 1899-
Undated (6 items) March 20, 1973, February 11, 1974
Shirer, William L. (William Lawrence), 1904-
August 13, 1936
Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965.
November 4, 1948, February 23, 1950, March 29, 1950, August 15, 1952, June 21, 1956, December 16, 1957, June 15, 1959, May 27, 1960
Sylvester, Arthur, 1901-
November 10, 1962